A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7 FA279
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
1924-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman
Commonwealth Fund
Harkness, Anna M. Richardson
Harkness, Edward Stephen
Harkness, Charles W.
FA279
3.59 Cubic Feet 9 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in 5 subseries:
Subseries 1 Board Meetings, Annual Meetings of the Corporation, and Special Meetings
Subseries 2 Financial Statements
Subseries 3 General Files
Subseries 4 Reports of the Board of Directors
Subseries 5 Special Reports
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: meeting minutes, financial statements, and reports.
Child mental health; New York (N.Y.); Child welfare; Child psychology; Hygiene; Education, Rural; Legal issues; Law; Medical education; Legal research; Medicine, Rural; Medical research; Mental health; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; War relief; Public health; New York (State); United States; Public welfare; Social Science Research Council; Phillips Exeter Academy; Columbia University; Yale University; Harvard University
- Board Meetings, Annual Meetings of the Corporation and Special Meetings, 1
  - Agendas, December 26, 1956-March 20, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, December 2, 1924-November 10, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, December 2, 1924-November 10, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, December 2, 1924-November 10, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, December 2, 1924-November 10, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, December 2, 1924-November 10, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, December 2, 1924-November 10, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, December 2, 1924-November 10, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, February 9, 1972-September 25, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, February 9, 1972-September 25, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, February 9, 1972-September 25, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, February 9, 1972-September 25, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, February 9, 1972-September 25, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, February 9, 1972-September 25, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Notices, December 26, 1956-November 13, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Retreat, March 30-April 20, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Financial Statements, 2
  - October 23, 1918 to June 30, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - October 23, 1918 to June 30, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - October 23, 1918 to June 30, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - October 23, 1918 to June 30, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - October 23, 1918 to June 30, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - October 23, 1918 to June 30, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - June 30, 1961 to June 30, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - June 30, 1961 to June 30, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - June 30, 1961 to June 30, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- General Files, 3
  - Chapman, Carleton B., February 20, 1973-November 17, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Commission on Medical Education, May 31, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Conference on Alternatives for Future Commonwealth Fund Programs, October 19, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Conference on Bioethics in Medical Education, December 7, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Corporate Foundations, January 24-April 23, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Dunlop, John (Harvard University), July 20-November 20, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Evaluation of Commonwealth Fund Grants (R. H. Fitz Report), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Evaluation of Commonwealth Fund Grants (Quigg Newton Report), 1977 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Evaluation of Commonwealth Fund Grants (Walter Donway and M. Lipkin Report), 1978 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Foundation Surveys, April 9, 1975-October 14, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Health Legislation, June 14-November 29, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Humanities in Premedical Education, July 20, 1978-March 1, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Library Job Analysis, May-June 1966 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Luncheon Meeting on Corporate Foundations, March 8, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Meeting on Private Foundations and Medical Education, May 14, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Meeting on Privately Sponsored Commissions, December 12, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Memoranda on Evaluations, February 5, 1973-September 15, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - National Health Care Policy and Health Systems Group, October 24, 1973-March 31, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - National Health Insurance, October 10-December 20, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Program Directions, 1976-1978 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Program Directions, 1976-1978 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Program Discussions, December 21, 1977-January 11, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Program Review, October 2, 1963-March 24, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Study of Major Foundations, August 16, 1978-October 5, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 50)
- Reports of the Board of Directors, 4
  - September 30, 1921 to June 30, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - September 30, 1921 to June 30, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - September 30, 1921 to June 30, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - September 30, 1921 to June 30, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - September 30, 1921 to June 30, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - September 30, 1921 to June 30, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - June 30, 1958 to June 30, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - June 30, 1958 to June 30, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - June 30, 1958 to June 30, 1980, June 30, 1958 to June 30, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 59)
- Special Reports, 5
  - Commonwealth Fund Fellowships to Graduates of the Universities of the United Kingdom, A Review - 1925-1955, April 1957 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Medical Education, November 1955, November 1957, April and October 1959 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Medical Research, November 1953 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Medical Research Review #1 1931-1936 (September 1936), #2 1936-1944 (September 1946), 1931-1936 (September 1936),1936-1944 (September 1946) (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Medical Research Review #3 1944-1951 (February 1953), #4 1952-1958 (January 1960), 1944-1951 (February 1953), 1952-1958 (January 1960) (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Mental Health Projects (Review by Iago Galdston), January 1959 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Nursing (Harry E. Handley), February 1958 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Special Report on General Policy (Donal Sheehan), March 1948 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Special Report on Programs and Policy (Malcolm P. Aldrich), May 1957 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Study and Report on Medical Education (Paul J. Sanazaro), January 1962 (Box 9, Folder 69)